Finding Aid for Jack van der Velde papers, 1979-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jack van der Velde papers 1979-1994, 1985-1990
Van ver Velde, Jack
3.5 linear feet
03170 Aa 2
Professor Jack van der Velde is Professor Emeritus in the Physics Department of the University of Michigan. His papers focus on the IMB collaboration, which conducted underground experiments to detect proton decay from 1982-1991 in an effort to find experimental proof of the Grand Unified Theory of physics. They also observed neutrinos from a supernova for the first time. The papers mainly consist of meeting notes, research notes, the development of papers, and publications derived from the data.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (donor # 8954 ) were transferred by Professor Jack van der Velde on April 18, 2000.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
Professor Jack van der Velde is Professor Emeritus in the Physics Department of the University of Michigan, as of 2003. He received his Ph.D. in physics from the University of Michigan in 1958. That year, he began teaching physics at the University of Michigan as an instructor, and continued teaching there for his entire career. His research focused on high energy physics, cosmic rays, proton decay, and neutrinos.
Professor van der Velde was co-spokesman for the IMB Project (University of California-Irvine, University of Michigan, Brookhaven National Laboratory), with Frederick Reines. The IMB Project searched for proton decay using an 8,000 metric ton cube of water and a Cherenkov detector, located in the Morton Salt Company Mines in Fairport Harbor, Ohio.
The purpose of the project was to measure the stability of the proton. They were trying to gather the first conclusive evidence of the quark-lepton interactions predicted by the grand unification theory. If protons decayed as predicted, the decay would result in fast moving particles, which would produce Cherenkov light that the sensors would detect.
The theoretical models predicting the stability of the proton were developed in the fall of 1978. By December 1978, plans for the IMB collaboration were forming, a process that continued through May 1979. At that time, the proposal was finished and applications were made for funding. The detector was constructed beginning in January 1980 and was ready to begin collecting data July 31, 1982. The detector was upgraded to IMB-3 (after a short-lived IMB-2 phase) that had four times the sensitivity, which began producing data in September 1986. The University of Michigan had to withdraw from the collaboration at the end of 1989 due to other experiment responsibilities. In March 1991, the IMB-3 detector sprung a fatal water leak, ending data collection after 10 years. Physicists continued to publish and analyze the data for several years, including physicists from the University of Michigan until 1995.
Funding for the project came from the United States Department of Energy, which is a significant source of funding for grand unification theory research projects. The IMB received their approval for funding November 28, 1979. To start the project, the IMB collaborators depended on funds approved by then vice-president Shapiro from the University of Michigan in July 1979, and some funding from the University of California-Irvine.
A major achievement of the IMB project was the detection of neutrinos from a supernova (SN1987a) in 1987. This was the first time neutrinos had been detected from a supernova.
Additional information on the project is available at Professor Jack van der Velde's website http://www-personal.umich.edu/~jcv/
The papers all pertain to the IMB Experiments. They are divided into seven subseries: Collaborative Meeting Notes, Student Theses, Talks, Publications, Proposals, Research Notes and Memos, and Scholarly Community.
Subjects:
Van der Velde, Jack C.; Cherenkov counters.; Grand unified theories (nuclear physics); Physics.; Protons--Decay.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Van der Velde, Jack C.; Protons--Decay.; Laboratories.; Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Collaborative Meeting Notes
  Collaborative Meeting Notes (1.25 linear ft.) is arranged chronologically and includes agendas, data and data analysis, and making decisions. Meetings were held 3-4 times a year, from 1983 to 1990. Meetings to organize the IMB collaboration and experiments are recorded from 1979 to 1982. Also included is Professor van der Velde's notebook from PDK meetings, 1981-1984, with his notes and calculations.
  - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - 1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981-1984 (PDK notes, van der Velde's notebook) (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Box 1)
  - 1983, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1984, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1985 (4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1986, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - 1987, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1988, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1989, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1990 (Box 2)
- Student Theses
  Student Theses consists of nine theses written by students from research connected with IMB, from 1983 to 1990. Most theses focus on nucleon decay or the detection of neutrinos.
  - An Experimental Limit on Proton Decay: p= e+ + p, 1983 (Box 2)
  - A Search for Nucleon Decay into Lepton and k p, 1983 (Box 2)
  - A Search for Nucleon Decay: p=vK +, p=vK *+ and n=vK *p, 1984 (Box 2)
  - A Search for Nucleon Decay into 35 Two-and Three-Body Modes 1985 (Box 2)
  - A Search for Astrophysical Point Sources of Neutrinos using a Large Underground Water Cerenkov Detector 1985 (Box 2)
  - A Search for Nucleon Decay Employing Particle Identification, Invariant Masses, and Complete Track Reconstruction in a Water Cherenkov Detector 1987 (Box 2)
  - Recherche de Muons Souterrains en Provenance de la Direction de Cygnus X-3 dans le Detecteur de Frejus, Cygnus X-3 a Haute Energie: Entre ou ne pas entre 1987 (Box 2)
  - Observation of neutrinos from Stellar Collapse 1988 (Box 2)
  - Experimental Neutrino Physics and Astrophysics with the IMB-3 Detector 1990 (Box 2)
- Talks
  Talks (0.25 linear ft.) consists of notes and publications used to prepare for giving talks related to the IMB experiment results, some typed copies of the talks given, and photocopies of transparencies used for the presentations. Some talks were given by Professor van der Velde, and others by other members of the IMB collaboration. They cover four major speech topics: review of experiments, monopoles, neutrinos, and the supernova. Talks were given every few years, from 1980 to 1989.
  - Review of Experiments 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Monopole 1983 (Box 2)
  - IMB First Announcement of SN1987a (supernova), Moriond, France March 9, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Neutrino Astronomy (1989 Ginosar) 1989 (Box 2)
- Publications
  Publications (0.5 linear ft.) includes papers written by collaboration members and by other scientists on related subjects, as well as data and calculations. Publications may be in draft or published form. Some have several drafts with collaboration critiques. Also included is the debate over a paper published by a collaboration member without approval. Papers focus on proton decay or neutrinos detected from the supernova. There are also a memo listing all the papers produced by the collaboration up to 1990, a 1991 interview of Professor van der Velde for a study on collaborations in high-energy physics, and the 1989 talk given by co-spokesperson F. Reines accepting the Rossi prize at the AAS meeting on behalf of the collaboration.
  - The Research News: Description of the IMB experiments 1981 (Box 3)
  - Nucleon Decay and Baryon Number 1978-1982, 1990 (Box 3)
    (several papers)
  - Search for Proton Decay into e + + p in the IMB-3 Detector, 1990 (Box 3)
    (paper and data, peer review)
  - IMB (Proton Decay) 1983-1994 (Box 3)
    (several papers, mostly in Physical Review Letters. 1991 interview transcript. 1989 Rossi reward acceptance speech)
  - Angular Distribution of Events from SN1987a 1988 (Box 3)
    (drafts and data)
  - Possible Evidence for a New Particle from SN1987a 1989 (Box 3)
    (drafts, related papers, peer response)
  - Neutrinos, Muons, Underground Experiments, Proton Decay Experiments 1983-1987 (Box 3)
    (several papers, peer review)
  - Possible Observation of Neutrinos from Cygnus X-3 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    (drafts, memos, related articles)
  - Unapproved Publication by Collaboration Member: Limits on a Neutrino Lifetime 1986 (Box 3)
    (drafts)
  - Unapproved Publication Consequences 1988 (Box 3)
- Proposals
  Proposals (0.25 linear ft.) covers both plans for future experiments and funding and equipment proposals. It includes the original experiment proposal. The series also includes a report on the progress of construction from April 1981 and an evaluation of the project by TACUP (Technical Assessment Committee of University Programs) from 1983.
  - Correspondence Justifying the Experiment 1979 (Box 3)
  - Original IMB Proposal 1979 (Box 3)
  - IMB Construction, DOE Request, Budget Analysis April 1981 (Box 3)
  - Supplementary Apparatus Funding to Complete the Proton Decay Detector 1981 (Box 3)
    (includes progress report)
  - IMB Upgrade Proposal 1983 (Box 3)
  - Upgrade of IMB detector 1983 (Box 3)
  - Consensus Evaluation of High Energy Physics Program at University of Michigan by TACUP 1983 (Box 3)
  - Experiment Proposals 1980, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Nucleon Lifetime Experiment (Box 3)
  - Jack van der Velde at Washington (Box 3)
    (presentation of data)
- Research Notes and Memos
  Research Notes and Memos (0.5 linear ft.) includes data print outs, data analysis and calculations, and memos between collaboration members as they determine the meaning of the data. Also included is a chronology of the University of Michigan's involvement with the IMB collaboration. There are nine slides of the construction of the detector and 21 slides of experiment results, and a photograph of Professor van der Velde standing on top of the IMB pool.
  - Chronology of the Experiments (Box 4)
  - Slides of construction and results, with descriptions (Box 4)
  - Photograph of Professor van der Velde (Box 4)
  - PDK Memos 1980 (Box 4)
  - QCAL'S mod E CAL's 1986 (Box 4)
  - Ec Calibrations 1988 (Box 4)
  - IMB Research Notes 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Data Analysis August 1988-February 1989 (Box 4)
  - Data (Box 4)
- Scholarly Community
  Scholarly Community (0.25 linear ft.) encompasses interaction between the IMB collaboration and the rest of the scientific community. These papers include requests for collaboration publications, debate within the collaboration over what data to share, and arrangements with Smithsonian World and National Geographic.
  - Solar v and Cosmic Rays 1981 (Box 4)
    (conferring within and beyond the collaboration on a potential experiment)
  - Smithsonian World and National Geographic 1983 (Box 4)
  - Sharing Unpublished Data Outside Collaboration Debate 1989 (Box 4)
    (concerns the paper A Sub-millisecond Neutrino Pulsar in SN1987a by Arnon Dar)